Part Two
Yes, yes, hello there, Araragi-senpai.
こんにちは:hello/good day (daytime greeting), 先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
はいはいこんにちはですよ 阿良々木先輩
This is Ougi Oshino.
野[の, や]:plain|hidden (structural) member|wild|, 扇[おうぎ, おおぎ]:folding fan
忍野扇です
Now today, we will be studying
about constellations.
星座[せいざ]:constellation/star sign/zodiac sign, 勉強[べんきょう]:study|diligence|discount
では今日は 星座についてのお勉強をしましょうね
I realized right away
that this was a dream.
夢[ゆめ]:dream, 気付く[きづく]:to notice/to recognize/to recognise
すぐにこれは夢なのだと気付いた
For Araragi-senpai, who lives in Japan, the
constellations in the southern skies may be difficult.
日本[にほん, にっぽん]:Japan, 住まい[すまい, じゅうきょ]:dwelling/house/residence, 先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 南天[なんてん, ナンテン]:southern sky|heavenly bamboo (Nandina domestica)/nandina, 星座[せいざ]:constellation/star sign/zodiac sign, 厳しい[きびしい]:severe/strict|intense (e.g. cold)
日本住まいの阿良々木先輩からすれば
南天の星座は厳しいでしょうね
Though my rival, Hanekawa-senpai, may perhaps
be looking at them now from around Australia.
ライバル:rival/competition, 先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, ひょっと:possibly/perhaps|unintentionally, 今頃[いまごろ]:about this time, オーストラリア:Australia, あたり:hit|success, あたり:on the bank of/by the side of (e.g. a river, pond)|(in the) neighbourhood, ご覧になる[ごらんになる]:to see/to look|try to, しれる:to become known/to come to light|to be known
私のライバルである羽川先輩は
ひょっとしたら今頃オーストラリアあたりでご覧になっているかもしれませんが
No, but really,
いや本当
the southern hemisphere has many unfamiliar
constellations, so it is amusing.
南半球[みなみはんきゅう]:southern hemisphere, 馴染み[なじみ]:intimacy/friendship/familiarity, 星座[せいざ]:constellation/star sign/zodiac sign, たくさん:a lot/lots|enough, 面白い[おもしろい]:interesting|amusing|pleasant
南半球には馴染みのない星座がたくさんありますから
面白いものですよ
There is Chameleon over that way.
あちら:that way (direction distant from both speaker and listener)/over there|that one (something physically distant from both speaker and listener, or something not visible but known by both speaker and listener), カメレオン座[カメレオンざ]:Chamaeleon (constellation)/the Chameleon
あちらにはカメレオン座とかありますからね
There's also Pictor (easel) and Vela (sail).
画架座[がかざ]:Pictor (constellation)/the Easel, 帆座[ほざ]:Vela (constellation)/the Sails
あとは画架(がか)座とか 帆(ほ)座とか
There's even a constellation
called Hydrus (water snake).
水蛇座[みずへびざ]:Hydrus (constellation)/the Water Snake
水蛇(みずへび)座 というのもありますねえ
Water Snake
Snake—with a "water" radical
I guess it's what we would call
the Hydra (sea snake).
こちら:this way (direction close to the speaker or towards the speaker)/this direction|here (place close to the speaker or where the speaker is), 海蛇座[うみへびざ]:Hydra (constellation)/the Sea Serpent
こちらで言うところの海蛇座でしょうかね
Surely you know of this one, the Hydra?
ご存知[ごぞんじ]:knowing|(an) acquaintance, 海蛇座[うみへびざ]:Hydra (constellation)/the Sea Serpent
これはご存知ですよね 海蛇座
It's the biggest of the 88 constellations.
星座[せいざ]:constellation/star sign/zodiac sign, 最大[さいだい]:biggest/greatest/largest
八十八の星座の中で 最大の星座です
Though, it's difficult to determine how the
size of a constellation is measured.
星座[せいざ]:constellation/star sign/zodiac sign, 大きさ[おおきさ]:size/dimensions/volume, 風[ふり]:swing|appearance|pretence (pretense)||, 風[かぜ]:wind|manner|cold, 計る[はかる]:to measure/to weigh|to conjecture, 難しい[むずかしい, むつかしい]:difficult|fussy|gloomy||
ま 星座の大きさをどういう風に計るかというのも
難しいところですけれどね
When you think of it three-dimensionally,
it pretty much falls apart.
立体的[りったいてき]:three-dimensional, 捉える[とらえる]:to catch|to grasp (e.g. meaning)|to captivate, 割と[わりと]:relatively/comparatively
立体的に捉えると 割とバラけちゃいますし
However, the presence
that this Hydra has...
海蛇座[うみへびざ]:Hydra (constellation)/the Sea Serpent, 存在感[そんざいかん]:presence (impressive quality)
ただ 海蛇座のこの存在感は
...reminds one of Kiss-shot
Acerola-orion Heart-under-blade.
アセロラオリオン:acerola (Malpighia glabra)/Barbados cherry, アセロラオリオン:Orion, ハート:heart, アンダー:under, ブレード:blade, 連想[れんそう]:association (of ideas)/being reminded (of something)/suggestion
キスショット・アセロラオリオン・ハートアンダーブレードを
連想させますよね
They call the creature
in Hydra a "sea snake",
そもそも:in the first place/to begin with|... the heck (e.g. "what the heck?"), 海蛇座[うみへびざ]:Hydra (constellation)/the Sea Serpent, 海蛇[うみへび, ウミヘビ]:sea snake|worm eel (Ophichthidae spp.)/snake eel
そもそも海蛇座 海蛇とは言いますが
but it actually points to
the legendary hydras.
伝説[でんせつ]:tradition/legend/folklore, ヒドラ:Hydra, 示す[しめす]:to (take out and) show|to point out (finger, clock hand, needle, etc.)|to indicate
これは伝説上 ヒドラのことを示しているのです
Do you know what a hydra is?
ヒドラ:Hydra
わかりますか? ヒドラ
It's not an exaggeration
to say it's immortal.
不死身[ふじみ]:invulnerability/immortality/insensibility to pain, 過言[かごん, かげん]:exaggeration/saying too much|misstatement
不死身と言っても過言ではない
It's a monster that keeps regenerating
no matter how much you cut off.
斬る[きる]:to kill (a human) using a blade (sword, machete, knife, etc.)/to slice (off)/to lop (off), 再生[さいせい]:resuscitation|reformation|playback||, 怪物[かいぶつ]:monster
斬っても斬っても再生する怪物です
The one that defeats that hydra is
the famous, courageous Heracles.
ヒドラ:Hydra, 退治[たいじ]:extermination (e.g. of pests, demons, bandits)|making someone renounce worldly desires in order to concentrate on Buddha's teachings|curing illness, 有名[ゆうめい]:famous|fame, 勇猛[ゆうもう, ゆうみょう]:daring/bravery/valor, ヘラクレス:Hercules/Herakles
そのヒドラを退治するのは
有名な 勇猛な ヘラクレスなのですが
You probably cannot defeat Kiss-shot
Acerola-orion Heart-under-blade with this method,
アセロラオリオン:acerola (Malpighia glabra)/Barbados cherry, アセロラオリオン:Orion, ハート:heart, アンダー:under, ブレード:blade, 倒す[たおす]:to throw down|to kill|to overthrow|, 倒す[こかす]:to knock down/to knock over
このやりかたでは
キスショット・アセロラオリオン・ハートアンダーブレードは倒せないでしょうが
but he chopped the nine heads
of the hydra one by one,
ヒドラ:Hydra, 九[きゅう, く]:nine, 九[チュー]:nine, 首[くび, クビ]:neck|head|dismissal, 首[しゅきゅう, しるし]:decapitated head of an enemy, 順[じゅん, ずん]:order/turn|obedient, 斬る[きる]:to kill (a human) using a blade (sword, machete, knife, etc.)/to slice (off)/to lop (off)
ヒドラの九つある首を順に斬り
and burnt the cut sections shut with a
flame to prevent them from regenerating.
切り口[きりくち]:cut end/section|point of view, 炎[ほのお, ほむら]:flame/blaze|flames (of intense emotion, e.g. love, jealousy, anger), 炎[えん]:-itis (indicating an inflammatory disease), 焼く[やく]:to burn|to roast|to heat||, 塞ぐ[ふさぐ]:to stop up|to stand in the way|to occupy||, 再生[さいせい]:resuscitation|reformation|playback||
切り口を炎で焼いて塞(ふさ)ぎ
再生できないようにしたのです
As a side note, during this fight
between Heracles and the hydra,
余談[よだん]:digression/sequel (of a story), 海蛇[うみへび, ウミヘビ]:sea snake|worm eel (Ophichthidae spp.)/snake eel, ヘラクレス:Hercules/Herakles, 戦い[たたかい]:battle/fight/struggle, 際[きわ, ぎわ]:edge/brink|time, 際[さい]:on the occasion of/circumstances/juncture
余談ですが この海蛇とヘラクレスとの戦いの際
the crab from Cancer sided with the
hydra and attacked Heracles.
海蛇[うみへび, ウミヘビ]:sea snake|worm eel (Ophichthidae spp.)/snake eel, 味方[みかた]:friend/ally/supporter, ヘラクレス:Hercules/Herakles, 攻撃[こうげき]:attack/strike|criticism, 蟹座[かにざ]:Cancer (constellation)/the Crab, 蟹[かに, カニ]:crab
海蛇の味方をしてヘラクレスを攻撃したのが
蟹座の蟹なのです
It used its big claws you know
of to cut at Heracles.
例[れい]:custom|said|instance|, 例[ためし]:precedent/example, 大きな[おおきな]:big/large/great, 鋏[はさみ, ハサミ]:scissors/shears|hole punch, 鋏[やっとこ]:pincers/nippers/pliers, ヘラクレス:Hercules/Herakles, 切りつける[きりつける]:to cut at/to slash at
例の大きな鋏(はさみ)で
ヘラクレスに切りつけました
Its attitude of challenging a giant
enemy with a small weapon is,
小さな[ちいさな]:small/little/tiny, 武器[ぶき]:weapon/arms|weapon (something used to gain an advantage), 大きな[おおきな]:big/large/great, 敵[かたき]:rival|revenge|spouse, 敵[てき]:opponent/rival|menace, 挑む[いどむ]:to challenge/to throw down the gauntlet|to pressure someone for sex, 姿勢[しせい]:attitude/posture/stance
小さな武器で大きな敵に挑む姿勢は
in fact, Senjougahara-senpai herself.
まさしく:surely/no doubt/evidently, 先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
まさしく戦場ヶ原先輩そのものですね
When you awaken, please tell
Senjougahara-senpai about this episode,
目が覚める[めがさめる]:to awaken/to perk up/to snap out (of something), 辺り[あたり, ほとり]:on the bank of|(in the) neighbourhood|around (Sunday, last year, etc...)|, エピソード:episode/anecdote/vignette, 先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 話す[はなす]:to talk|to tell|to speak (a language)
目が覚めたらこの辺りのエピソードを戦場ヶ原先輩に話して
so that you can be well-liked.
是非[ぜひ]:certainly/without fail|right and wrong, もてる:to be able to possess (hold, get, etc.)|to be well liked/to be popular, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
是非とももててくださいよ
Serpens, the one that isn't Hydra,
海蛇座[うみへびざ]:Hydra (constellation)/the Sea Serpent, 蛇座[へびざ]:Serpens (constellation)/the Snake
そして 海蛇座ならぬ蛇座のほうも
is also a symbol of immortality,
though not as much as the hydra.
ヒドラ:Hydra, 不死身[ふじみ]:invulnerability/immortality/insensibility to pain, 性[さが, なりくせ]:one's nature/one's destiny|custom, 性[せい]:nature (of a person)|sex|gender|, 象徴[しょうちょう]:symbol, ではある:to be (in contrast to something that is not the case)
ヒドラでこそありませんが
不死身性の象徴ではありますからね
After all, Serpens has a special
characteristic that you can say
なにせ:at any rate/anyhow, 蛇座[へびざ]:Serpens (constellation)/the Snake, 全天[ぜんてん]:all heaven, 星座[せいざ]:constellation/star sign/zodiac sign
なにせ この蛇座というのは全天八十八星座の中でも
is unique among all 88
constellations in the sky.
唯一[ゆいいつ, ゆいつ]:only/sole/unique, 変わる[かわる]:to change|to move to|to be different, 特徴[とくちょう]:feature/trait/characteristic, 持つ[もつ]:to hold (in one's hand)|to possess|to maintain||
唯一と言っていい
変わった特徴を持っていますからね
Do you know what it is, Araragi-senpai?
ご存知[ごぞんじ]:knowing|(an) acquaintance, 先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
なんだかご存知ですか? 阿良々木先輩
I don't know.
Does Ougi-chan know what it is?
扇[おうぎ, おおぎ]:folding fan
扇ちゃんは知っているのだろうか
I don't know anything.
私は何も知りませんよ
It's what you know, Araragi-senpai.
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
あなたが知っているんです 阿良々木先輩
In reality, you should know what it is.
御存知[ごぞんじ]:knowing|(an) acquaintance
御存知のはずですよ 本当は
See, like this.
風[ふり]:swing|appearance|pretence (pretense)||, 風[かぜ]:wind|manner|cold
ほら こういう風に
Serpens is the only constellation that exists
split up into the eastern and western parts.
蛇座[へびざ]:Serpens (constellation)/the Snake, 東西[とうざい, ひがしにし]:east and west|Orient and Occident|Ladies and Gentlemen!, 分断[ぶんだん]:dividing into parts, 存在[そんざい]:existence/being, 星座[せいざ]:constellation/star sign/zodiac sign
蛇座は東西に分断されて存在する
ただひとつの星座なのです
As a snake... It has been chopped up.
蛇[へび, じゃ]:snake|serpent/large snake, ぶつ切りにする[ぶつぎりにする]:to cut into chunks/to chop into lumps
蛇として ぶつ切りにされている
This clearly shows immortality.
不死身[ふじみ]:invulnerability/immortality/insensibility to pain
これは 見るからに不死身ですよね
It's still alive despite its
body chopped in half.
身体[からだ]:body|torso|build||, 身体[しんたい, しんだい]:body/physical system/person, 真[しん]:truth|seriousness|logical TRUE||, 真[ま]:just|pure|truth, 二[に, ふた]:two, 二[アル]:two, 生きる[いきる]:to live|to make a living|to be in effect||, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation
身体を真っ二つにされても生きているだなんて
Well, Araragi-senpai, you seem to have your
body chopped into half rather often as well.
Actually, in the gap where it is split up, a
different constellation has been drawn in.
実[じつ, じち]:truth|sincerity|content|, 実[み]:fruit|seed|(in broth) pieces of meat, vegetable, etc.|, 分断[ぶんだん]:dividing into parts, 狭間[はざま]:interval|valley|loophole (in a wall), 星座[せいざ]:constellation/star sign/zodiac sign, 描く[えがく, かく]:to draw|to depict|to picture in one's mind|
実を言いますと 分断されたその狭間には
別の星座が描かれているのですよ
I'm sure you know of it, Araragi-senpai,
but it's Ophiuchus (snake charmer).
絶対[ぜったい]:absolutely|absolute|absoluteness, 先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, ご存知[ごぞんじ]:knowing|(an) acquaintance, 蛇遣い座[へびつかいざ]:Ophiuchus (constellation)/the Serpent Bearer
これは絶対に阿良々木先輩はご存知だと思いますが
蛇遣い座です
The picture depicts the snake charmer
holding the upper and lower halves...
蛇遣い[へびつかい]:snake charmer, 蛇[へび, じゃ]:snake|serpent/large snake, 半身[はんしん]:half the body/half length, 半身[はんみ]:stance with legs in an L-shape, with one leg bent in front and other extended behind (martial arts, traditional theater), 下半身[かはんしん, しもはんしん]:lower half of body
蛇遣いが 蛇の上半身と下半身を
...of the snake's body with his left
and right arms, respectively.
左腕[さわん, ひだりうで]:left arm|left-handed (baseball pitcher), 右腕[みぎうで, うわん]:right arm|right-hand man|right-handed pitcher, それぞれ:each/respectively, 持つ[もつ]:to hold (in one's hand)|to possess|to maintain||, 図[ず]:drawing/picture|sight
左腕右腕でそれぞれ持っているという図になるのですよ
If I recall, that snake charmer was
Asklepios, dubbed the sage physician?
確か[たしか]:sure|reliable|If I'm not mistaken, 蛇遣い[へびつかい]:snake charmer, 医聖[いせい]:great doctor/sage physician, 呼ぶ[よぶ]:to call out (to)|to summon (a doctor, etc.)|to invite||
確か あの蛇遣いは医聖と呼ばれる
アスクレピオスなのだっけ?
Sage physician
That's right. Nothing less from you,
Araragi-senpai. You really have extensive knowledge.
さすが:as one would expect|still/all the same, さすが:dagger, 先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 博識[はくしき]:extensive knowledge, いらっしゃる:to come/to go|is (doing)
そうですね さすが阿良々木先輩
博識でいらっしゃる
Asklepios' medical skills were
honed remarkably quickly,
医術[いじゅつ]:medicine/healing art, 技[わざ, ぎ]:technique/art/skill, めきめき:remarkably/markedly|sound of breaking or creaking, 洗練[せんれん]:polish/refinement
アスクレピオスの医術の技は
めきめきと洗練され
and it got to a point where he
could even resurrect the dead.
しまい:sisters, しまい:end/close|noh dance in plain clothes, 死人[しにん, しびと]:corpse/dead person, 蘇る[よみがえる]:to be resurrected/to be resuscitated|to be recalled (e.g. memories), レベル:level/standard/amount, 達する[たっする]:to reach/to get to/to arrive at
しまいには死人さえも蘇(よみがえ)らせるレベルにまで達したのです
However, that was going too far.
過ぎ[すぎ]:past/after|too (much)
けれど これはやり過ぎだった
Going too far. Against the rules.
過ぎ[すぎ]:past/after|too (much), ルール:rule, 違反[いはん]:violation/offense/offence, 違反[いへん]:breaking (a contract, promise, etc.)
やり過ぎ ルール違反
I guess you could say it went
against the logic of the world.
世[よ]:world/society/age, 世[せい]:counter for generations|epoch, 理[り]:reason|general principle (as opposed to individual concrete phenomenon)|(in neo-Confucianism) the underlying principles of the cosmos, 理[ことわり]:reason/truth/way of things, 反する[はんする]:to be contrary to|to act contrary to (rules or guidelines)|to oppose
世の理(ことわり)に反すると言いますかね
Bringing forth anger of Hades
the god of the underworld,
冥王[めいおう]:Hades (Greek god)/Pluto (Roman god), 怒りを買う[いかりをかう]:to rouse anger/to provoke wrath/to offend
冥王(めいおう)ハーデスの怒りを買い
Asklepios was struck by lightning
and literally sent to heaven.
雷[かみなり, いかずち]:lightning|god of thunder|anger, 雷[なるかみ]:thunder, 打つ[うつ]:to hit|to strike (noon, etc.)|to beat (rhythmically, e.g. pulse, waves, etc.)||, 打つ[ぶつ]:to hit (a person)/to strike/to beat, 文字[もじ, もんじ]:letter (of alphabet)/character|literal, 通り[とおり]:avenue|coming and going|flow (of water, air, etc.)||, 通り[どおり]:in accordance with|roughly|Street, 天[てん, あめ]:sky|heaven|svarga (heaven-like realm visited as a stage of death and rebirth)|, 召す[めす]:to call|to eat|to put on||
アスクレピオスは雷に打たれて
文字通り天に召されたというわけです
Well, bringing a person back to life -- to
mass-produce immortals -- is quite the sin.
生き返る[いきかえる]:to revive/to come to oneself/to be restored to life, 不死身[ふじみ]:invulnerability/immortality/insensibility to pain, 量産[りょうさん]:mass production, 結構[けっこう]:splendid|sufficient|well enough||, 罪[つみ]:crime|penalty|fault|
まあ 人を生き返らせるというのは
不死身を量産するというのは 結構な罪ということですよ
Yotsugi Ononoki-chan is also among those
who were resurrected after death, but...
斧[おの]:axe/hatchet, 余接[よせつ]:cotangent, 死後[しご]:after death, 生きる[いきる]:to live|to make a living|to be in effect||, 一人[ひとり, いちにん]:one person|alone/unmarried, ではある:to be (in contrast to something that is not the case)
斧乃木余接ちゃんも
死後に生き返らされた一人ではありますが
Tadatsuru Teori
All parties responsible for
her resurrection faced retaliation...
生き返る[いきかえる]:to revive/to come to oneself/to be restored to life, 当事者[とうじしゃ]:person concerned/interested party/related party, 全員[ぜんいん]:all members (unanimity)/all hands/the whole crew, しっぺ:bamboo stick used to strike meditators into greater wakefulness (in Zen Buddhism)|striking someone's wrist with one's index and middle finger, 返し[かえし]:reversal|return gift|barb (on a fishing hook)|
彼女を生き返らせた当事者は全員
そのしっぺ返しで
Yoduru Kagenui
Meme Oshino
Deishu Kaiki
...and had curses placed
upon their bodies.
身[み]:body|oneself|one's place|, 身[むくろ]:(dead) body/corpse, 呪い[のろい]:curse/spell/malediction, 呪い[まじない]:charm/incantation/spell, 受ける[うける, ウケる]:to receive|to catch (e.g. a ball)|to be struck by (wind, waves, sunlight, etc.)||
その身に呪いを受けましたからね
Hm? What's this about?
Curses?
If that's the case, what's
going to happen?
となるとどうなんでしょうねえ
What kind of penalty will Gaen-san pay in the
future for reviving Araragi-senpai from hell?
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 地獄[じごく]:hell, 復活[ふっかつ]:revival (e.g. musical)/come-back|restoration, 今後[こんご]:from now on/hereafter, 一体[いったい]:...the heck (e.g. "what the heck?")|one object|one form||, どんな:what/what kind of|(with -temo, demo, etc.) any(body, thing, means, etc.), 報い[むくい]:reward/recompense/return, 受ける[うける, ウケる]:to receive|to catch (e.g. a ball)|to be struck by (wind, waves, sunlight, etc.)||, ことになる:it has been decided (so) that/it has been arranged (so) that|it is the result (of)
阿良々木先輩を地獄から復活させた臥煙さんは
今後一体どんな報いを受けることになるのでしょうねえ
Izuko Gaen
Ha-hah...
はっはー
Ougi-chan, if you're going to sit
down, sit on my left side.
扇[おうぎ, おおぎ]:folding fan, 座る[すわる]:to sit|to assume (a position)|to hold steady, 左側[ひだりがわ, さそく]:left/left (hand) side
扇ちゃん 座るなら左側に
Hmm? Why is that?
どうしてです?
That's Senjougahara's seat.
席[せき]:seat|location (of a gathering, etc.)|position, 席[むしろ, えん]:woven mat (esp. one made of straw)|seat
そこは戦場ヶ原の席だから
My oh my, that is not a cheap seat.
やおや:greengrocer, 安い[やすい]:cheap/inexpensive|calm
おやおや これはお安くありませんねえ
Well, please don't worry.
心配[しんぱい]:worry/concern|care
まあ ご心配なく
I have never had any intentions of taking
over the throne of the main heroine.
メイン:main/principal part, ヒロイン:heroine, 座[ざ]:seat|status|gathering||, 脅かす[おどかす]:to threaten/to menace|to startle, 脅かす[おびやかす]:to intimidate/to scare|to jeopardize, 毛頭[もうとう]:not in the least/not at all/not a bit
私はメインヒロインの座を脅(おびや)かそうというつもりは毛頭ありませんよ
I wouldn't mind striving to be a
"little sister" character...
妹[いもうと]:younger sister, 妹[いも]:darling (only of a woman)|one's sister|friend, キャラ:(fictional) character, くらい:dark/gloomy|dark (in colour), くらい:approximately/about|to (about) the extent that, 目指す[めざす]:to aim at/to have an eye on|to go toward
妹キャラくらいなら目指してもいいところですが...
But, Karen-chan aside, I wouldn't want
to compete against Tsukihi-chan.
火[ひ]:fire/flame/blaze, 火[か]:Tuesday|fire (second of the five elements), ともかく:anyhow/anyway/somehow or other, 競う[きそう]:to compete with|to emulate
しかし火憐ちゃんはともかく
月火ちゃんとは競いたくはありませんかねえ
She is... Her true identity is...
正体[しょうたい]:true character/true form|consciousness
彼女は... 彼女の正体は
Tadatsuru Teori said it.
折[おり]:opportunity|fold|small food box (wooden or cardboard), 正弦[せいげん]:sine
手折正弦は言った
He told me at the bottom of hell.
地獄[じごく]:hell, 底[そこ]:bottom/sole, 底[てい]:base (logarithmic, exponential, number system)|base (triangle, cone, cylinder, etc.)|type, 教える[おしえる]:to teach|to tell|to preach
地獄の底で僕に教えてくれた
He mentioned the name of the client who
requested him to exterminate me and Shinobu...
退治[たいじ]:extermination (e.g. of pests, demons, bandits)|making someone renounce worldly desires in order to concentrate on Buddha's teachings|curing illness, 依頼[いらい]:request/commission|dependence, クライアント:client
彼は 僕や忍の退治を依頼したクライアントの名を...
Araragi-senpai. What do you
think is the right thing?
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 正しい[ただしい]:right/correct|proper
阿良々木先輩 正しさってなんだと思います?
Oh no, you don't have to think
too seriously about it.
It is difficult to be
doing the right thing.
正しい[ただしい]:right/correct|proper, 難しい[むずかしい, むつかしい]:difficult|fussy|gloomy||
正しいことをするというのは 難しいですからね
It is especially difficult to
do "just the right thing."
特に[とくに]:particularly/especially, 正しい[ただしい]:right/correct|proper, とても:very/awfully|(not) at all, 難しい[むずかしい, むつかしい]:difficult|fussy|gloomy||
特に "正しいことだけをする" というのは
とても難しいです
If you try to do the right thing, you
end up also having to do attachments,
正しい[ただしい]:right/correct|proper, しようとする:to try and do something/to attempt to do something, 付属[ふぞく]:attached/belonging (to)/included, 間違う[まちがう]:to make a mistake/to be incorrect/to be mistaken
正しいことをしようとすると
付属して 間違ったこと
wrong things or things that are not right.
正しい[ただしい]:right/correct|proper, ちゃあ:if (an action, etc.)|since .../if you are going to ...
正しくないこともしなくちゃあならなくなったりします
So that's why, Araragi-senpai.
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
だからですね 阿良々木先輩
To win, there is an absolute need
to lose somewhere along the way.
As long as you are being the right self,
you should not be doing the right thing.
正しい[ただしい]:right/correct|proper
正しい自分である上では
正しいことをするべきではないんですよ
In the end, if a mistake always accompanies
you when you try to do the right thing,
正しい[ただしい]:right/correct|proper, 必ず[かならず]:always/without exception/necessarily, 間違い[まちがい]:mistake|accident|improper conduct (e.g. between man and woman), 伴う[ともなう]:to accompany/to go hand in hand with|to be accompanied by
正しいことをしようとすれば
必ずそこに間違いが伴う
and if that's the case...
というのであれば...
In the end it all balances out to zero.
結局[けっきょく]:after all|conclusion|ending of a game of Go, 差し引き[さしひき]:deduction/subtraction|ebb and flow, しまう:to finish/to stop|to close (a business, etc.)
結局差し引きゼロになってしまいますからね
Therefore, the way of life that Kagenui-san
and the Fire Sisters practice
影[かげ]:shadow|reflection|ominous sign||, ファイヤー:fire, 実践[じっせん]:practice/putting into practice|praxis (philosophy), 生きざま[いきざま]:attitude to life/form of existence/way of life
ですから 影縫さんやファイヤーシスターズが
実践している生きざまは
is something they claim to be justice.
達[たち]:pluralizing suffix (esp. for people & animals; formerly honorific), 達[だち, ダチ]:friend, 自身[じしん]:by oneself/personally, 正義[せいぎ]:justice/right/righteousness, 名乗る[なのる]:to give one's name (as)|to claim to be|to reveal oneself (as)||
彼女達自身は正義を名乗っていますけれど
But, it is not necessarily
"doing the right thing."
決して[けっして, けして]:never/by no means/not in the least, 正しい[ただしい]:right/correct|proper, ではある:to be (in contrast to something that is not the case)
決して "正しいことをしている" わけではありません
To stay the right selves, they
do not do the right thing,
達[たち]:pluralizing suffix (esp. for people & animals; formerly honorific), 達[だち, ダチ]:friend, 正しい[ただしい]:right/correct|proper
彼女達は正しい自分であるために
正しいことをするのではなく
MISTAKES
but correct mistakes...
間違い[まちがい]:mistake|accident|improper conduct (e.g. between man and woman), 正す[ただす]:to correct|to adjust|to ascertain|
間違いを正す...
INJUSTICE
... and correct injustice. That is
the way of life they choose.
不正[ふせい]:injustice/unfairness/iniquity, 正す[ただす]:to correct|to adjust|to ascertain|, 生きる[いきる]:to live|to make a living|to be in effect||, 方[かた]:direction|person|method of||, 方[ほう]:direction|side (of an argument, etc.)|type||, 選ぶ[えらぶ]:to choose/to select
不正を正す...
そういう生き方を選んでいるのです
EXAMINE (tadasu)
Examine (tadasu)...
糺す[ただす]:to ascertain/to confirm/to verify, あるいは:or/possibly, 問い質す[といただす]:to enquire of someone about something (inquire)/to question|to interrogate
糺す あるいは問い質す
とも言いますがね
...or Inquire a question (toi-tadasu),
I guess you could say.
INQUIRE (tadasu)
In other words, your foe's foe is not your
ally, but by becoming a foe against evil,
敵[かたき]:rival|revenge|spouse, 敵[てき]:opponent/rival|menace, 味方[みかた]:friend/ally/supporter, 悪[あく]:evil/wickedness, 悪[わる]:bad thing/bad person
つまり 敵の敵は味方ではありませんけれど
悪の敵となることで
by becoming the antonym to evil, you
assign yourself justice, so to say.
悪[あく]:evil/wickedness, 悪[わる]:bad thing/bad person, 対義語[たいぎご]:antonym, 己[おのれ]:oneself (itself, etc.)|I|you||, 己[おれ, おらあ]:I/me, 正義[せいぎ]:justice/right/righteousness, 任ずる[にんずる]:to appoint/to nominate/to assume (responsibility)
悪の対義語となることで
己に正義を任ずるということですかね
And I am also one that seeks the type
of "right" that corrects mistakes.
間違い[まちがい]:mistake|accident|improper conduct (e.g. between man and woman), 正す[ただす]:to correct|to adjust|to ascertain|, タイプ:type/kind/sort, 正しい[ただしい]:right/correct|proper, 追い求める[おいもとめる]:to pursue
そして私もまた 間違いを正すタイプの
正しさを追い求める者です
It is my role to eject those
that have broken the rules.
ルール:rule, 違反[いはん]:violation/offense/offence, 違反[いへん]:breaking (a contract, promise, etc.), 退場[たいじょう]:exit (from a stage)/exeunt|leaving, 命じる[めいじる]:to order/to command/to appoint, 役割[やくわり]:part/assigning (allotment of) parts/role
ルール違反をした者に退場を命じるのが
私の役割です
TO SCATTER (kakusan)
Broken the rules...
ルール:rule, 違反[いはん]:violation/offense/offence, 違反[いへん]:breaking (a contract, promise, etc.)
ルール違反...
TO DISPERSE (musan)
...ejection.
退場[たいじょう]:exit (from a stage)/exeunt|leaving
退場
Araragi-senpai, the program
is about to end.
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, そろそろ:slowly/quietly|soon, プログラム:program/programme, 終わる[おわる]:to finish/to end/to close
阿良々木先輩
そろそろプログラムが終わります
It's better for you to
wake up now, isn't it?
目を覚ます[めをさます]:to wake up|to sober up/to come to one's senses
目を覚ましたほうがいいですよ?
You should at least continue to enjoy
恋[こい]:(romantic) love, 相手[あいて]:companion|other party|opponent (sports, etc.), デート:date/go on a date
恋する相手とのデートを
the rest of your date with the
person you're in love with.
後[あと]:behind|after|after one's death||, 後[のち]:later|future|after one's death|, 精々[せいぜい]:at the most/at best/to the utmost, 楽しむ[たのしむ]:to enjoy (oneself), くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
この後も精々楽しんできてくださいよ
But, since you have the
chance, Araragi-senpai...
折角[せっかく]:with trouble|rare|kind|, 先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
でも 折角ですから阿良々木先輩
Please think about the answer to
the question of what you think
正しい[ただしい]:right/correct|proper, 問い[とい]:question/query, 答[こたえ, いらえ]:answer/reply/response
正しさってなんだと思うかという問いの答は
is the right thing when you
have to kill some time.
暇潰し[ひまつぶし]:waste of time/killing time, 考える[かんがえる]:to think about|to ponder|to intend||, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
暇潰しに考えておいてください
Let's talk about it again when
I see you in real life.
現実[げんじつ]:reality/actuality/hard fact, 世界[せかい]:the world|sphere|renowned|, お話し[おはなし]:story/tale
現実世界で会ったときに
それについてお話ししましょう
Yeah, I got it.
If I still remember when I wake up.
But really, what in the world
is your true identity?
何者[なにもの]:who/what kind of person
だけどきみは本当に何者なんだい?
That too will be discussed
the next time I see you.
お話し[おはなし]:story/tale, もらう:to receive/to take|to get somebody to do something
それも またお会いしたときにお話しさせてもらいますよ
But well, if I were to force myself to
say what I can say at this moment...
言える[いえる]:to be possible to say/to be able to say, 限り[かぎり]:limit|degree|as far as possible||, 限り[きり]:end|bounds|delivery date (of a futures contract)||, 強いる[しいる]:to force/to compel/to coerce
まあでも 今 言える限りのことを強いて言うなら
I am...
私は...
...the principles of the universe.
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 法則[ほうそく]:law/rule
宇宙の法則ですよ
Space map...
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 地図[ちず]:map
宇宙地図...
...in the shape of a hand fan (ougi).
扇[おうぎ, おおぎ]:folding fan, 形[かたち, よう]:form/shape|visage, 形[かた, がた]:shape|collateral|obverse of an old "zeni" coin
扇の形
Pitch black vacuum...
and unbalanced galaxies.
真っ黒[まっくろ]:pitch black, 真空[しんくう]:vacuum/hollow/empty, 偏る[かたよる]:to be one-sided/to incline/to be partial, 銀河[ぎんが]:Milky Way|galaxy
真っ黒な真空に... 偏った銀河
Don't think about this too hard, either.
深い[ふかい]:deep|profound|dense||, 考える[かんがえる]:to think about|to ponder|to intend||, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
これも深く考えないでください
Now that you came back from hell, and returned
to being completely human, Araragi-senpai...
地獄[じごく]:hell, 蘇る[よみがえる]:to be resurrected/to be resuscitated|to be recalled (e.g. memories), 完全[かんぜん]:perfection/completeness, 戻る[もどる]:to turn back (e.g. half-way)|to return|to recover (e.g. something lost)|, 戻る[もとる]:to go against/to act contrary to/to deviate from, 先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
地獄から蘇り
今や完全なる人間に戻った阿良々木先輩とは
Surprisingly enough, I may no longer have to be
concerned with you anymore... if things go well.
案外[あんがい]:unexpectedly/surprisingly|unexpected, 以上[いじょう]:not less than|beyond ... (e.g. one's means)|above-mentioned||, 関わる[かかわる]:to be affected|to be concerned with|to stick to (opinions), 済む[すむ]:to finish|to merely result in something less severe than expected|to feel at ease|, しれる:to become known/to come to light|to be known, あわよくば:if there is a chance/if possible/if circumstances permit
案外私は これ以上関わらずに済むかもしれませんから
あわよくば
So, please.
ですから
I beg of you, don't get suckered
into Gaen-san's slick talk.
お願い[おねがい]:request/wish|please, 口車[くちぐるま]:cajolery/wheedling, 乗る[のる]:to get on (train, plane, bus, ship, etc.)|to get on (e.g. a footstool)|to reach||, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
お願いですから 臥煙さんの口車に乗らないでくださいね
Concerning Kiss-shot Acerola-orion
Heart-under-blade now in her complete form,
完全[かんぜん]:perfection/completeness, 体[からだ]:body|torso|build||, 体[たい]:body|shape|substance||, アセロラオリオン:acerola (Malpighia glabra)/Barbados cherry, アセロラオリオン:Orion, ハート:heart, アンダー:under, ブレード:blade
完全体となったキスショット・アセロラオリオン・ハートアンダーブレードや
or Mayoi Hachikuji who has,
after resting in peace, returned again,
成仏[じょうぶつ]:entering Nirvana/becoming a Buddha|going to heaven, ながら:while/during|while, この世[このよ]:this world/the present life (in contrast to the land of the dead), 舞い戻る[まいもどる]:to come back
成仏しておきながら またもこの世に舞い戻った
got lost again, within this world...
迷い[まよい]:hesitation/bewilderment|inability to reach enlightenment, 戻る[もどる]:to turn back (e.g. half-way)|to return|to recover (e.g. something lost)|, 戻る[もとる]:to go against/to act contrary to/to deviate from, 寺[てら]:temple (Buddhist), 寺[じ]:counter for temples
迷い戻った八九寺真宵について
This time, I expect, from
the bottom of my heart,
今度[こんど]:this time|next time|recently, 見捨てる[みすてる]:to abandon/to fail/to desert, 正しい[ただしい]:right/correct|proper, 判断[はんだん]:judgment|divination|judgement
今度こそ "見捨てる" という正しい判断をされることを
that you'll make the right
decision to forsake them...
期待[きたい]:expectation/anticipation/hope
私は心から期待しますよ
Araragi-senpai.
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
阿良々木先輩
I woke up.
I woke up?
Senjougahara....
戦場ヶ原...
I'm not asleep.
寝る[ねる]:to lie down|to go to bed|to sleep (lying down)||
寝てないわ
I'm not asleep at all.
全然[ぜんぜん]:not at all (with neg. verb)|wholly/entirely, 寝る[ねる]:to lie down|to go to bed|to sleep (lying down)||
全然寝てない
I'm not asleep at all. I was just
thinking with my eyes shut.
全然[ぜんぜん]:not at all (with neg. verb)|wholly/entirely, 寝る[ねる]:to lie down|to go to bed|to sleep (lying down)||, 目を瞑る[めをつぶる, めをつむる]:to shut one's eyes|to ignore|to die, 考え事[かんがえごと]:something to think about/one's thoughts/concern
全然寝てない
目を瞑(つむ)って考え事をしていただけ
I'm sorry. I was actually asleep.
なさる:to do, 寝る[ねる]:to lie down|to go to bed|to sleep (lying down)||
ごめんなさい 本当は寝ていました
It's fine. I was asleep for a bit, too.
寝る[ねる]:to lie down|to go to bed|to sleep (lying down)||
大丈夫 僕もちょっと寝ちゃってたから
I see. I guess it means
we were both tired?
互い[たがい]:mutual/reciprocal, 疲れる[つかれる]:to get tired|to be worn out (e.g. of well used objects)|to starve, かしら:I wonder, かしら:head|hair (on one's head)
そう お互い疲れていたということかしら
I guess it was too hasty to go on a date
after we only decided on it yesterday.
さすが:as one would expect|still/all the same, さすが:dagger, 昨日[きのう, さくじつ]:yesterday, デート:date/go on a date, 突貫[とっかん]:charge/rush/lightning attack, 工事[こうじ]:construction work/construction/work (related to construction, e.g. painting, concrete-pouring, etc.), 過ぎる[すぎる]:to pass through|to pass (i.e. of time)|to have expired||, 過ぎる[よぎる]:to go by/to cross/to pass by
さすがに昨日の今日でデートというのは
突貫工事過ぎたわね
So, what kind of plans did
you have after this?
先[さき]:previous|point (e.g. pencil)|head (of a line)||, 先[せん]:former/previous|first move (in go, shogi, etc.), どういう:somehow/how/in what way, 予定[よてい]:plans/arrangement/schedule
で ここから先はどういう予定になっているんだ?
We're going to learn the state-of-the-art
science at the adjoining science museum.
併設[へいせつ]:joint establishment (esp. schools of different levels or different courses of study)/establishment as an annex (e.g. of a school)/juxtaposition, 科学館[かがくかん]:science museum, 現代[げんだい]:nowadays/modern era/modern times, 最[さい]:the most/the extreme|prime, 新鋭[しんえい]:young and energetic/up-and-coming/new and excellent, 科学[かがく]:science, 学ぶ[まなぶ]:to study (in depth)/to learn/to take lessons in
併設の科学館で現代の最新鋭の科学を学ぶのよ
After doing a tour of the science
museum, we'll have lunch.
科学館[かがくかん]:science museum, 一[いち]:one|best|first||, 一[ひとつ]:one|for one thing|only||, 周[しゅう]:Zhou (dynasty of China)|perimeter|counter for laps or circuits, 昼食[ちゅうしょく, ちゅうじき]:lunch/midday meal|food served at a tea party (tea ceremony)
科学館を一周したあとは 昼食よ
The plan was to study during the morning,
午前中[ごぜんちゅう]:in the morning/during the morning, 勉強[べんきょう]:study|diligence|discount, プラン:plan
午前中はお勉強プランだったから
Floor Map
so I have mainly leisurely activities
planned for the afternoon.
午後[ごご]:afternoon/p.m., 遊び[あそび]:playing|play (margin between on and off, gap before pressing button or lever has an effect), メイン:main/principal part, 据える[すえる]:to place (in position)|to install|to settle (upon something)|
午後は遊びをメインに据えているわ
We'll go out to the city by car, and
spend the first half bowling.
町[まち, ちょう]:town|street|109.09 m||, 前半[ぜんはん, ぜんぱん]:first half, ボウリング:bowling (esp. tenpin)
クルマでちょっと町まで出て
前半はボウリング
After a bit of tea time, we'll spend
the second half singing karaoke.
ティータイム:teatime/tea break/coffee break, 挟む[はさむ]:to interpose/to hold between|to be on either side (e.g. road), 挟む[さしはさむ]:to insert|to interrupt|to harbor (e.g. doubts), 後半[こうはん]:second half/latter half, カラオケ:karaoke (singing to taped accompaniment)
ティータイムを挟んで 後半はカラオケよ
Oh...
Araragi-kun, what's your
high score in bowling?
ボウリング:bowling (esp. tenpin)
阿良々木くん ボウリングのハイスコアは?
Well, I'm a novice at bowling altogether,
like I don't think I've ever played before.
ボウリング:bowling (esp. tenpin), 自体[じたい]:itself|one's own body|originally, 初心者[しょしんしゃ]:beginner, たぶん:informing, たぶん:perhaps/probably|generous
いや ボウリング自体初心者で
たぶんやったことないと思うんだけど
Got it. There will be a
penalty on the loser.
負ける[まける]:to lose|to succumb|to be inferior to||, 罰[ばち]:(divine) punishment/curse/retribution, 罰[ばつ]:punishment/penalty, ゲーム:game
わかった 負けたら罰ゲームね
Don't set up a penalty after it came
to light that I'm a novice!
初心者[しょしんしゃ]:beginner, 判明[はんめい]:establishing/proving/ascertaining, 罰[ばち]:(divine) punishment/curse/retribution, 罰[ばつ]:punishment/penalty, ゲーム:game, 設定[せってい]:establishment/creation|options setting
僕が初心者と判明してから罰ゲームを設定するな
The loser must swear absolute
obedience to the winner.
敗者[はいしゃ]:the defeated/vanquished/loser, 勝者[しょうしゃ]:winner/victor, 命令[めいれい]:order/command|(software) instruction, 絶対[ぜったい]:absolutely|absolute|absoluteness, 服従[ふくじゅう]:obedience/submission/resignation
敗者は勝者の命令に絶対服従
That's a really harsh penalty!
罰[ばち]:(divine) punishment/curse/retribution, 罰[ばつ]:punishment/penalty, ゲーム:game, 重い[おもい]:heavy|heavy (feeling)|slow||
罰ゲームが重いよ!
Dammit... To think that Araragi-kun
would actually lie to me...
おのれ:oneself (itself, etc.)|I/me, まさか:by no means/never!|something unexpected, 嘘をつく[うそをつく, ウソをつく]:to tell a lie/to fib, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation
おのれ... まさか阿良々木くんが私に嘘をつくなんて
You're not a novice at all.
全然[ぜんぜん]:not at all (with neg. verb)|wholly/entirely, 初心者[しょしんしゃ]:beginner
全然初心者じゃないじゃない
KOYOKOYO
HITAGI
From about the first frame
till about the fifth frame,
第[だい]:prefix for forming ordinal numbers, 一[いち]:one|best|first||, 一[ひとつ]:one|for one thing|only||, フレーム:frame, 五[ご, いつ]:five, 五[ウー]:five, あたり:hit|success, あたり:on the bank of/by the side of (e.g. a river, pond)|(in the) neighbourhood
第一フレームから第五フレームあたりまでは
HITAGI
KOYOKOYO
she showed amazing skill.
見事[みごと]:splendid|praiseworthy act|utter (esp. defeat), 腕前[うでまえ]:ability/skill/facility
見事な腕前だった
HITAGI
KOYOKOYO
However, starting at the sixth
frame, her playing...
第[だい]:prefix for forming ordinal numbers, 六[ろく, む]:six, 六[リュー]:six, フレーム:frame, 以降[いこう]:on and after/as from/hereafter, プレイ:play/erotic play (esp. S&M)
しかし第六フレーム以降 彼女のプレイは
HITAGI
KOYOKOYO
LIMITS OF ACTIVITY
HITAGI
KOYOKOYO
...suddenly changed.
Completely changed...
一転[いってん]:one turn/spinning around|complete change, 一変[いっぺん]:complete change/about-face
一転した 一変した
Right.
疲れる[つかれる]:to get tired|to be worn out (e.g. of well used objects)|to starve
そう 戦場ヶ原は疲れたのである
Senjougahara was exhausted.
Seems that her arm went numb.
腕[うで]:arm|skill/efforts, 腕[かいな]:arm (esp. upper arm)|counter used to measure the thickness of round objects, 痺れる[しびれる]:to become numb/to go to sleep (e.g. a limb)|to be excited, らしい:seeming ... (expresses judgment based on evidence, reason or trustworthy hearsay)/appearing ...|-ish
腕が痺(しび)れたらしい
KOYOKOYO
HITAGI
Fine. I will admit defeat.
負け[まけ]:defeat/loss/losing (a game), 認める[したためる]:to write up, 認める[みとめる]:to recognize|to deem|to approve||
いいわ 負けを認めるわよ
You can order me to do anything.
命令[めいれい]:order/command|(software) instruction
なんでも命令するがいいわ
So, I wonder what kind of lewd
request will you make of me?
どんな:what/what kind of|(with -temo, demo, etc.) any(body, thing, means, etc.), エッチ:H/h, 要求[ようきゅう]:demand/firm request/requisition, かしら:I wonder, かしら:head|hair (on one's head)
さあ どんなエッチな要求をしてくれるのかしら?
My anticipation only heightens.
期待[きたい]:expectation/anticipation/hope, 高まる[たかまる]:to rise/to swell/to be promoted, ばかり:only/merely|approximately
期待は高まるばかりだわ
Just for reference, if you
had won, Senjougahara,
ちなみ:association/link|pledge (esp. for marriage), 勝つ[かつ]:to win/to gain victory, 場合[ばあい]:case/situation
ちなみに戦場ヶ原が勝っていた場合は
what kind of request were
you going to make?
どんな:what/what kind of|(with -temo, demo, etc.) any(body, thing, means, etc.), 要求[ようきゅう]:demand/firm request/requisition
どんな要求をするつもりだったのか
I was going to make a lewd
request, of course!
当然[とうぜん]:natural/as a matter of course/justified, エロい:erotic/pornographic|eminent, 要求[ようきゅう]:demand/firm request/requisition
当然 エロい要求をするつもりだったわよ!
I struck a deal with something like, "Then
let's walk arm-in-arm until our tea time."
ティータイム:teatime/tea break/coffee break, 腕を組む[うでをくむ]:to fold one's arms|to link arms with someone, 歩く[あるく]:to walk, 辺り[あたり, ほとり]:on the bank of|(in the) neighbourhood|around (Sunday, last year, etc...)|, 手を打つ[てをうつ]:to take measures (in face of events being anticipated)|to come to an agreement (in bargaining, etc.)|to clap one's hands together
じゃあティータイムまで
腕を組んで歩こうという辺りで手を打った
Hmm... To think that you were having an adventure of
that sort on the actual day of the entrance exams.
ふうん:misfortune/bad luck/ill luck, ふうん:hmm/well ...|roughly, まさか:by no means/never!|something unexpected, 受験[じゅけん]:taking an examination (esp. school and university entrance), 当日[とうじつ]:appointed day/very day, アドベンチャー:adventure, 繰り広げる[くりひろげる]:to unfold/to unroll/to open
ふうん... まさか受験日当日に
そんなアドベンチャーを繰り広げていたとは
It's unexpected, but it's so
fitting for you, Araragi-kun...
意外[いがい]:unexpected/surprising, らしい:seeming ... (expresses judgment based on evidence, reason or trustworthy hearsay)/appearing ...|-ish
意外と言うか
阿良々木くんらしいと言うか...
Though, I have to ask, what in
the world were you doing?
何をやっているんだと言うか
it's unclear exactly what Gaen-san
is fighting against...
戦う[たたかう]:to make war (on)|to compete (against)|to struggle (against adversities, etc.), 定か[さだか]:definite/sure
臥煙さんが何と戦っているのかは定かではないけれども...
But perhaps you, Araragi-kun, are
the opponent of that battle.
ひょっと:possibly/perhaps|unintentionally, 相手[あいて]:companion|other party|opponent (sports, etc.), 戦う[たたかう]:to make war (on)|to compete (against)|to struggle (against adversities, etc.), しれる:to become known/to come to light|to be known
ひょっとしたら それは
阿良々木くんを相手に戦っているのかもしれないわよね
No, it's more of a hunch than any meaning.
意味[いみ]:meaning/significance, 直感[ちょっかん]:intuition/instinct/insight
いえ 意味と言うよりは直感なんだけれども
Compared to your stance, Araragi-kun, where you
can only see what is right in front of your eyes,
見える[みえる]:to be seen|to look|to come, 見える[まみえる]:to have an audience|to face (an enemy)|to serve (esp. as one's wife), 姿勢[しせい]:attitude/posture/stance
目の前のことしか見えない阿良々木くんの姿勢とは
that macroscopic stance Gaen-san takes would
clash no matter how you look at it.
たって:strongly hoping or requesting (of something that is difficult to be brought to fruition), たって:even if/even though|however, 巨視的[きょしてき]:macroscopic, スタンス:stance/attitude/standpoint, 対立[たいりつ]:confrontation/opposition/antagonism
どうしたって臥煙さんの巨視的なスタンスは
対立しそうだなって
Clash... or oppose, if you want
a slightly harsher term.
対立[たいりつ]:confrontation/opposition/antagonism, 少し[すこし]:small quantity|little while|short distance, 厳しい[きびしい]:severe/strict|intense (e.g. cold), 敵対[てきたい]:hostility/antagonism/opposition, かしら:I wonder, かしら:head|hair (on one's head)
対立 もう少し厳しく言うならば
敵対 かしら
We'll duke it out for two hours, and
the one who loses in total points...
二[に, ふた]:two, 二[アル]:two, 対決[たいけつ]:confrontation/showdown, 総合[そうごう]:synthesis/coordination|comprehensive, 得点[とくてん]:score/points made/marks obtained, 負ける[まける]:to lose|to succumb|to be inferior to||, 勝つ[かつ]:to win/to gain victory
二時間対決して
総合得点で負けたほうは勝ったほうに
Karaoke
Red-White Song Battle
...swears absolute obedience
to the winner.
絶対[ぜったい]:absolutely|absolute|absoluteness, 服従[ふくじゅう]:obedience/submission/resignation
絶対服従ね
Song: "Futakotome"
Setting: Original Key
I'll go first. You listen well.
先攻[せんこう]:batting first
先攻私 聞くがいいわ
Challenger: Hitagi-san                                            Song: Futakotome
Score: 82.107%
Analysis: You have very high singing skills,
but emotional expression seems slightly weak.
It will be better if you add
more intonation to your singing.
An 82...
点[ちょぼ, チョボ]:dot/point|gidayuu musicians (in kabuki), 点[てん]:spot|point|mark (e.g. in exam)||
82点
Lies.
嘘[うそ, ウソ]:lie|mistake|unwise move|
嘘
82 percent is a failing score. This is the
first time I've ever scored in the low eighties.
点[ちょぼ, チョボ]:dot/point|gidayuu musicians (in kabuki), 点[てん]:spot|point|mark (e.g. in exam)||, 赤点[あかてん]:failing mark (e.g. in exam), 生まれる[うまれる]:to be born, 初めて[はじめて]:for the first time|only after ... is it .../only when ... do you ..., 台[だい]:stand|support|counter for machines, incl. vehicles||, 台[うてな]:tower|stand|calyx, 前半[ぜんはん, ぜんぱん]:first half, 取る[とる]:to take|to steal|to eat||
82点って 赤点じゃない
生まれて初めて八十点台前半を取ったわ
What kind of test is it if 82
percent is a failing score?
点[ちょぼ, チョボ]:dot/point|gidayuu musicians (in kabuki), 点[てん]:spot|point|mark (e.g. in exam)||, 赤点[あかてん]:failing mark (e.g. in exam), どんな:what/what kind of|(with -temo, demo, etc.) any(body, thing, means, etc.), テスト:test
82点が赤点って どんなテストだよ
Araragi-kun, you spent the majority of your
high school career feeling like this?
高校[こうこう]:senior high school/high school, 生活[せいかつ]:living/life (one's daily existence)/livelihood, 大半[たいはん]:majority/more than half|mostly, 気分[きぶん]:feeling/mood, 過ごす[すごす]:to pass (time)|to overdo (esp. of one's alcohol consumption)|to take care of||
阿良々木くんは
高校生活の大半をこんな気分で過ごしてきたの...?
I was not able to understand it at all.
理解[りかい]:understanding/comprehension/appreciation, あげる:to raise/to elevate|to do up (one's hair)
理解してあげられてなかったわ
I was supposed to be a lot kinder to you.
もっと:(some) more/even more/longer, 優しい[やさしい]:tender/kind/gentle, あげる:to raise/to elevate|to do up (one's hair), いける:to arrange (flowers)/to plant|living, いける:to be good (at)/to go well|to look (taste, etc.) good
もっと優しくしてあげなきゃいけなかった
What kind of horrible things have
I been saying to Araragi-kun?
酷い[むごい]:cruel/merciless|tragic, 酷い[ひどい]:cruel|violent|very bad|
私はなんて酷いことを
阿良々木くんに言ってきたんだろう
You're saying those horrible
things right now.
酷い[むごい]:cruel/merciless|tragic, 酷い[ひどい]:cruel|violent|very bad|
酷いことは今言ってる
Song: chocolate
Setting: original key
Challenger: Koyokoyo-san                   Song: chocolate insomnia
Score: 82.438%
Analysis: All elements are coming together
at a very high level. Keep it up,
and 100% is not just a dream.
Loser - Red 819           RESULTS       Winner - White 822
And once again, I was the winner.
勝つ[かつ]:to win/to gain victory
そして勝ったのはまたも僕だった
Impossible... To think that I would lose
against Araragi-kun twice in one day.
馬鹿[ばか, バカ]:fool|trivial matter|foolish|, 一日[いちにち, いちじつ]:one day|first day of the month, 一日[つきたち]:first day of the month|first ten days of the lunar month, 二[に, ふた]:two, 二[アル]:two, 度[たび, たんび]:time (three times, each time, etc.)/times, 度[ど]:degree (angle, temperature, scale, etc.)|counter for occurrences and times|strength (of alcohol), 負ける[まける]:to lose|to succumb|to be inferior to||, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation
馬鹿な... この私が阿良々木くんに
一日のうちに二度も負けるだなんて
Now, feel free to give
me any order you want.
命令[めいれい]:order/command|(software) instruction
さあ 何でも命令するがいいわ
How about you carry me to
our car like a princess?
駐車場[ちゅうしゃじょう]:parking lot/parking place, 姫[ひめ]:young lady of noble birth|girl|small|, 抱っこ[だっこ]:(child's) hug/carrying a baby in one's arms/carrying a pet in one's arms, かしら:I wonder, かしら:head|hair (on one's head)
駐車場までお姫さま抱っこっていうのはどうかしら?
I'll kill you if you say I'm heavy.
重い[おもい]:heavy|heavy (feeling)|slow||
重いって言ったら殺すからね
Nothing less from you, Araragi-kun.
さすが:as one would expect|still/all the same, さすが:dagger
さすが阿良々木くん
It shows that you're used to cradling young
girls in your arms in everyday life.
普段[ふだん]:usual/habitual/ordinary, 幼女[ようじょ]:little girl, 抱っこ[だっこ]:(child's) hug/carrying a baby in one's arms/carrying a pet in one's arms, 慣れる[なれる]:to get used to|to become skilled in|to become tame
普段から幼女を抱っこし慣れているだけのことはあるわね
That particular expression
leads to misunderstandings.
I'd like you to stop that.
Hourly Parking
Entrance 50m ahead
Whew. That was embarrassing.
恥ずかしい[はずかしい]:shy/ashamed|disgraceful
ふう 恥ずかしかった
I just saw hell.
地獄[じごく]:hell
地獄を見たわ
You'd go that far?
そこまで言うか
MORE HELLISH THAN HELL
Senjougahara....
戦場ヶ原...
I have something important to talk about.
大事[だいじ, おおごと]:important/valuable|safe (Tochigi dialect), 話[はなし]:talk/speech|discussions, 話[わ]:counter for stories, episodes of TV series, etc.
大事な話があるんだが
If it's a request to get
married, I'm okay with it.
結婚[けっこん]:marriage, 申し込み[もうしこみ]:application/entry/request
結婚の申し込みならＯＫよ
No, it's not that important a topic.
大事[だいじ, おおごと]:important/valuable|safe (Tochigi dialect), 話[はなし]:talk/speech|discussions, 話[わ]:counter for stories, episodes of TV series, etc.
いや そこまで大事な話じゃない
And that was way too instant a reply.
返事[へんじ]:reply/answer/response, 過ぎる[すぎる]:to pass through|to pass (i.e. of time)|to have expired||, 過ぎる[よぎる]:to go by/to cross/to pass by
そしてふたつ返事過ぎる
IT TURNED INTO A MARRIAGE PROPOSAL
Actually, it's about a gift in return for the
chocolate I received for Valentine's Day...
実[じつ, じち]:truth|sincerity|content|, 実[み]:fruit|seed|(in broth) pieces of meat, vegetable, etc.|, バレンタインデー:Valentine's Day, 頂く[いただく]:to receive|to eat|to be crowned with||, チョコレート:chocolate, 返し[かえし]:reversal|return gift|barb (on a fishing hook)|, 件[くだん]:the aforementioned/the said|the usual, 件[けん]:matter/case/item
実は バレンタインデーに頂いた
チョコレートのお返しの件なんだが
I haven't been able to get one ready.
用意[ようい]:preparation/arrangements/provision
用意できてないんだ
I'm sorry. I didn't have
time to get one ready.
なさる:to do, 用意[ようい]:preparation/arrangements/provision
ごめんなさい 用意する時間がなかった
In thinking of what to get,
I thought way too much.
考える[かんがえる]:to think about|to ponder|to intend||, 過ぎる[すぎる]:to pass through|to pass (i.e. of time)|to have expired||, 過ぎる[よぎる]:to go by/to cross/to pass by, しまう:to finish/to stop|to close (a business, etc.)
考えているうちに考え過ぎてしまって
HONEST MAN
So, can you wait two or three more days?
二[に, ふた]:two, 二[アル]:two, 三[さん, み]:three|tri-, 三[サン]:three, もらえる:to be able to receive/to be able to take|could you (give me)
なので二 三日待ってはもらえないだろうか
THINKING TOO MUCH
Of course, I'll tack on the interest
accrued during that period.
もちろん:of course/certainly/naturally, 利息[りそく]:interest (bank), 上乗せ[うわのせ]:adding/addition/extra
もちろん その分の利息は上乗せするから
What, you were worried about such a thing?
気に病む[きにやむ]:to worry/to fret (over something)/to be worried
なんだ そんなことを気に病んでいたの
It was enough for me that you went on
a date with me the whole day today.
一日[いちにち, いちじつ]:one day|first day of the month, 一日[つきたち]:first day of the month|first ten days of the lunar month, デート:date/go on a date, 十分[じっぷん, じゅっぷん]:10 minutes, 十分[じゅうぶん]:plenty|division into ten|perfectly
今日一日 デートしてくれただけでも十分よ
It's fine for you to just give me
something when you feel like it.
気が向く[きがむく]:to feel like/to feel inclined to do, くらい:dark/gloomy|dark (in colour), くらい:approximately/about|to (about) the extent that
気が向いたら何かくれるくらいでいいわよ
It wasn't like I made that chocolate
expecting to receive something in return.
返し[かえし]:reversal|return gift|barb (on a fishing hook)|, 期待[きたい]:expectation/anticipation/hope, チョコレート:chocolate, 作る[つくる]:to make|to prepare (food)|to raise||
私はお返しを期待してチョコレートを作ったわけではないわ
Araragi-kun.
阿良々木くん
It's unforgivable.
許す[ゆるす]:to permit|to exempt (from fine)|to confide in|
許せないわね
Eh?
I can't hardly believe that, on White Day,
one of the three big events of the year for couples,
恋人[こいびと]:lover/sweetheart, 達[たち]:pluralizing suffix (esp. for people & animals; formerly honorific), 達[だち, ダチ]:friend, 三[さん, み]:three|tri-, 三[サン]:three, 大[おお]:big/large, 大[だい]:the large part of|big|approximate size||, イベント:event, ホワイトデー:White Day (March 14th)
あろうことか恋人達の三大イベントのひとつであるホワイトデーに
you don't have anything
prepared for your lover?
ラバー:lover, 対する[たいする]:to face (each other)|to be directed toward (the future, etc.)|to receive (a client, etc.)||, 用意[ようい]:preparation/arrangements/provision, してい:servant/janitor/messenger, してい:older sister and younger brother, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation
ラバーに対して何も用意していないだなんて
I have to doubt that you have
any affection towards me.
対する[たいする]:to face (each other)|to be directed toward (the future, etc.)|to receive (a client, etc.)||, 愛情[あいじょう]:love/affection, 疑う[うたがう]:to doubt/to distrust/to be suspicious of, 得る[うる]:to be able to .../can ...|to get, 得る[える]:to get|to understand|to receive something undesirable (e.g. a punishment)|
私に対する愛情を疑わざるを得ないわ
Eh? Ehh?
All day today, I was wondering exactly what
kind of surprise Araragi-kun had prepared for me.
一日[いちにち, いちじつ]:one day|first day of the month, 一日[つきたち]:first day of the month|first ten days of the lunar month, いったい:...the heck (e.g. "what the heck?")/...in the world (e.g. "why in the world?")|one object, いったい:region/zone/whole place, どんな:what/what kind of|(with -temo, demo, etc.) any(body, thing, means, etc.), サプライズ:surprise, 用意[ようい]:preparation/arrangements/provision
今日一日 阿良々木くんはいったいどんなサプライズを用意してくれているんだろうと
My heart was racing, and I was so excited...
But you didn't have anything ready.
どきどき:thump-thump/bang-bang|to beat fast (of one's heart), はらはら:to feel anxious/to feel nervous|fluttering down, わくわく:tremble/get nervous/excitedly, してい:servant/janitor/messenger, してい:older sister and younger brother, 準備[じゅんび]:preparation/setup/arrangements, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation
どきどきはらはらわくわくしていたのに
何の準備もなかっただなんて
What a sidestep that was!
肩透かし[かたすかし]:under-shoulder swing-down|dodging|disappointment
肩透かしもいいところよ
I had assumed that you would get me a
cruiser or something as a present.
てっきり:surely/certainly/beyond doubt, クルーザー:cruiser (i.e. warship or cabin cruiser), 一[いち]:one|best|first||, 一[ひとつ]:one|for one thing|only||, 台[だい]:stand|support|counter for machines, incl. vehicles||, 台[うてな]:tower|stand|calyx, くらい:dark/gloomy|dark (in colour), くらい:approximately/about|to (about) the extent that, プレゼント:present/gift
てっきり クルーザーの一台くらい
プレゼントしてくれるのかと思っていたのに
I-Isn't that expectation a bit too
mega-sized, don't you think?
期待[きたい]:expectation/anticipation/hope, 過ぎる[すぎる]:to pass through|to pass (i.e. of time)|to have expired||, 過ぎる[よぎる]:to go by/to cross/to pass by
そ それは期待がメガサイズ過ぎないかい?
Oh, brother. I wonder if I
should just kill myself.
自殺[じさつ]:suicide
あーあ 自殺しよっかなー
I-I'm sorry. That's why I'm apologizing.
謝る[あやまる]:to apologize/to apologise, じゃん:isn't it
ご ごめん だから謝ってるじゃん
Please don't commit suicide.
自殺[じさつ]:suicide, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
自殺はしないでください
T-Then, what can I do for
you to forgive me?
許す[ゆるす]:to permit|to exempt (from fine)|to confide in|
じゃ じゃあ どうすれば許してくれる?
I can't get you a cruiser, but
I'll do whatever I can-
クルーザー:cruiser (i.e. warship or cabin cruiser), 用意[ようい]:preparation/arrangements/provision, できる限り[できるかぎり]:as ... as one can/as ... as possible/as much as possible
クルーザーは用意できないけれど
できる限りのことなら
Did you just say you'll
do whatever you can?
できる限り[できるかぎり]:as ... as one can/as ... as possible/as much as possible
できる限りのことをするって言った? 今
Did you say absolute obedience?
絶対[ぜったい]:absolutely|absolute|absoluteness, 服従[ふくじゅう]:obedience/submission/resignation
絶対服従って言った?
N-No, I didn't say that...
い いえ 言ってませんけれど...
I did, I did! Indeed, I did say "absolute
obedience" with these lips!
絶対[ぜったい]:absolutely|absolute|absoluteness, 服従[ふくじゅう]:obedience/submission/resignation, まさに:exactly/surely|right then, 口[くち]:mouth|opening|mouth (of a bottle)||, 口[く, こう]:mouth/speech|counter for people or implements
言いました 言いました 絶対服従と
まさにこの口で言いました
I see. Nothing less from you,
Araragi-kun. Such a generous heart.
さすが:as one would expect|still/all the same, さすが:dagger, 度量[どりょう]:generosity/magnanimity|length and capacity, 広い[ひろい]:spacious/vast/wide
そう さすが阿良々木くん
その度量の広さ
You really are the man
I fell in love with.
惚れる[ほれる]:to fall in love/to be in love/to be charmed with
私が惚れた男ね
I've fallen in love with you over again.
惚れる[ほれる]:to fall in love/to be in love/to be charmed with, 直す[なおす]:to cure|to fix|to do over again (after -masu base of verb)||
惚れ直したわ
You don't know what I'm
going to request of you,
要求[ようきゅう]:demand/firm request/requisition, 一生[いっしょう]:whole life/a lifetime|(the only, the greatest, etc.) of one's life, お願い[おねがい]:request/wish|please, 絶対[ぜったい]:absolutely|absolute|absoluteness, 服従[ふくじゅう]:obedience/submission/resignation, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation
何を要求されるかもわからないのに
一生 私のお願いに絶対服従してくれるだなんて
but you're willing to be absolutely obedient
to my requests for the rest of your life.
The rest of my life!?
一生[いっしょう]:whole life/a lifetime|(the only, the greatest, etc.) of one's life
一生!?
S-Sure. The rest of my life.
一生[いっしょう]:whole life/a lifetime|(the only, the greatest, etc.) of one's life
お おう 一生だな
I got it. What should I do?
わかった 僕は何をすればいいんだ
Call my name.
呼ぶ[よぶ]:to call out (to)|to summon (a doctor, etc.)|to invite||
名前で呼んで
Call me... by my name.
私のこと 名前で
Eh?
I do call you. "Senjougahara."
呼ぶ[よぶ]:to call out (to)|to summon (a doctor, etc.)|to invite||, じゃん:isn't it
呼んでるじゃん 戦場ヶ原って
Not that. My first name,
with no honorifics.
呼び捨て[よびすて]:addressing someone without an honorific such as "san"
じゃなくて 下の名前で 呼び捨てに
So that's why she tried to set up a
penalty for bowling and karaoke.
ボウリング:bowling (esp. tenpin), カラオケ:karaoke (singing to taped accompaniment), 罰[ばち]:(divine) punishment/curse/retribution, 罰[ばつ]:punishment/penalty, ゲーム:game, 設ける[もうける]:to prepare ahead of time|to create/to establish, してい:servant/janitor/messenger, してい:older sister and younger brother
だからボウリングやカラオケで
罰ゲームを設けようとしていたのか
If it wasn't for an opportunity like this, it may
have been something I'd have never been able to say.
きっかけ:chance/start/cue, 言える[いえる]:to be possible to say/to be able to say, しれる:to become known/to come to light|to be known
こんなきっかけでもなければ
言えないことだったかもしれない
Absolute obedience for
the rest of my life.
一生[いっしょう]:whole life/a lifetime|(the only, the greatest, etc.) of one's life, 絶対[ぜったい]:absolutely|absolute|absoluteness, 服従[ふくじゅう]:obedience/submission/resignation
一生 絶対服従
Calling her by that name for
the rest of my life.
一生[いっしょう]:whole life/a lifetime|(the only, the greatest, etc.) of one's life, 呼ぶ[よぶ]:to call out (to)|to summon (a doctor, etc.)|to invite||, 続ける[つづける]:to continue/to keep up/to keep on
一生 その名を呼び続ける
...Hitagi.
ひたぎ
Thank you... Koyomi.
ありがとう:Thank you/Thanks, 暦[こよみ, れき]:calendar/almanac
ありがとう 暦
ARARAGI
Hello, Araragi-senpai.
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
やあ 阿良々木先輩
I've been waiting for you.
お待ちしておりましたよ
I've gotten tired of waiting.
待ちくたびれる[まちくたびれる]:to get tired of waiting
待ちくたびれました
I got exhausted just by waiting.
くたびれる:to get tired/to be exhausted|to wear out
待つだけでくたびれました
How was it?
いかが:how/in what way/how about
いかがでした?
Did you enjoy your last date
with Senjougahara-senpai?
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 最後[さいご]:last|no sooner than|one's final moments, デート:date/go on a date, 楽しめる[たのしめる]:to be able to enjoy
戦場ヶ原先輩との
最後のデートは楽しめましたか?
At the least, I was being considerate and
avoided butting in over on the physical world.
一応[いちおう]:more or less|tentatively|just in case|, 気を遣う[きをつかう]:to pay attention to another's needs/to attend to/to fuss about, 現実[げんじつ]:reality/actuality/hard fact, 世界[せかい]:the world|sphere|renowned|, 割り込む[わりこむ]:to cut in/to thrust oneself into/to wedge oneself in, 控える[ひかえる]:to be temperate in|to make notes|to be in preparation for||
一応気を遣って
現実世界での割り込みは控えておいたんですけれど
I'd like you to be appreciative of that.
感謝[かんしゃ]:thanks/gratitude, いただく:to receive/to get|to eat
感謝していただきたいものですねえ
I will be appreciative.
感謝[かんしゃ]:thanks/gratitude
感謝はする
But, how you said "the last date"
creates misunderstanding.
最後[さいご]:last|no sooner than|one's final moments, デート:date/go on a date, 誤解[ごかい]:misunderstanding, 招く[まねく]:to invite|to beckon|to call in|
ただ 最後のデートっていう言いかたは
誤解を招くな
It was merely the last date
of my high school life.
あくまで:to the end/to the bitter end|after all, 高校[こうこう]:senior high school/high school, 生活[せいかつ]:living/life (one's daily existence)/livelihood, 最後[さいご]:last|no sooner than|one's final moments, デート:date/go on a date
あくまでも 高校生活
最後のデートだ
So is it? Yes, that would be nice if it is...
It'd be nice if the two of you had a future.
二人[ふたり, ににん]:two persons/two people/pair, 未来[みらい]:the future (usually distant)|future tense|the world to come
です か ええ だったらいいですよねえ
お二人に 未来があればいいですよねえ
Ougi-chan. Did you try to exterminate me?
扇[おうぎ, おおぎ]:folding fan, 退治[たいじ]:extermination (e.g. of pests, demons, bandits)|making someone renounce worldly desires in order to concentrate on Buddha's teachings|curing illness
扇ちゃん きみは 僕を退治しようとしたの?
You asked a specialist to do such a thing?
専門家[せんもんか]:specialist/expert/professional, 依頼[いらい]:request/commission|dependence
そんなことを 専門家に依頼したの?
Oh, you heard from someone...
of such false rumors?
おや 誰かから聞きましたか? そんなデマを
But still, that is a sad false alarm...
悲しい[かなしい]:sad/sorrowful, 誤報[ごほう]:misinformation/incorrect report
しかしそれは悲しい誤報ですね
I would like an explanation.
釈明[しゃくめい]:explanation/vindication, 欲しい[ほしい]:wanted/wished for|I want (you) to
釈明させて欲しいところです
There is no way I would do anything
to harm you, Araragi-senpai.
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 害する[がいする]:to injure|to kill|to hinder
私が阿良々木先輩を
害するようなことをするわけがないじゃありませんか
That's why I told you, right?
だから言ったでしょう?
That I am expecting you, Araragi-senpai,
to make the right decision...
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 正しい[ただしい]:right/correct|proper, 判断[はんだん]:judgment|divination|judgement
阿良々木先輩が正しい判断をして
...and withdraw, instead of getting
suckered into Gaen-san's slick talk.
口車[くちぐるま]:cajolery/wheedling, 乗る[のる]:to get on (train, plane, bus, ship, etc.)|to get on (e.g. a footstool)|to reach||, 退く[どく, のく]:to step aside/to move (i.e. out of the way)|to resign, 退く[しりぞく, しぞく]:to step back|to withdraw (from the presence of a superior)|to resign|, 期待[きたい]:expectation/anticipation/hope
臥煙さんの口車に乗ることなく
退(ひ)いてくれることを期待します と
Did you say that?
言ったっけな
Well...
If she is saying she said
it, she probably said it.
But, it's nonexistent. The choice of forsaking
Shinobu and Hachikuji is something I don't have.
寺[てら]:temple (Buddhist), 寺[じ]:counter for temples, 見捨てる[みすてる]:to abandon/to fail/to desert, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation, 選択肢[せんたくし]:choices/alternatives/options
だけど ないぜ
忍や八九寺のことを見捨てるなんて選択肢は 僕には
There is no choice. I have no
surplus within my heart.
選択[せんたく]:selection/choice/option, 余地[よち]:place/room/margin, 余り[あまり, あんまり]:remainder|not very (with negative sentence)|surplus|
選択の余地はない
僕の心に余りはない
I don't know what the right thing is, but
I do know what path I should take.
正しい[ただしい]:right/correct|proper, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation, 選ぶ[えらぶ]:to choose/to select, 道[みち]:road|distance|the way (of proper conduct, etc.)||, 道[どう]:road|way|Buddhist teachings||
正しさが何かなんてわからないけれど
自分の選ぶべき道はわかっている
I wish you wouldn't hurry to
conclusions like that...
結論[けつろん]:conclusion, 急ぐ[いそぐ]:to hurry/to rush/to hasten, 欲しい[ほしい]:wanted/wished for|I want (you) to
そう結論を急がないで欲しいものですけれど
But well, that's fine. I tried to ask you
because I had nothing left to lose.
駄目元[だめもと, ダメもと]:giving something a try because one has nothing to lose, 訊く[きく]:to hear|to listen (e.g. to music)|to ask||
でもまあ そうですね 私としても
駄目元で訊いてみただけです
That said, it's disappointing.
とは言え[とはいえ]:though/although/be that as it may, 残念[ざんねん]:deplorable/bad luck/regret
とは言え残念です
For me personally, I'd like to see you,
Araragi-senpai, retire voluntarily right about now.
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 勇退[ゆうたい]:bowing out/retiring voluntarily, 願う[ねがう]:to desire|to beg|to have something done for oneself
私としては 阿良々木先輩には
ここらでご勇退願いたいんですけれどね
But egging you on to do so too much
would be going beyond my bounds.
あまり:remainder/rest|not very (with negative sentence), 促す[うながす]:to urge/to press/to prompt, 領分[りょうぶん]:territory/domain/dominion, しまう:to finish/to stop|to close (a business, etc.)
あまりそれを促すのも
領分を出てしまいますか
Hey, Araragi-senpai.
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
ねえ 阿良々木先輩
Let me correct one thing that you may
have a misunderstanding about.
勘違い[かんちがい]:misunderstanding/wrong guess, しれる:to become known/to come to light|to be known, 訂正[ていせい]:correction/revision/amendment, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
ひとつ あなたが勘違いされているかもしれないことを
訂正させてくださいよ
Misunderstanding? What is
the misunderstanding?
勘違い[かんちがい]:misunderstanding/wrong guess
勘違い? 勘違いって... 何?
I am not the "darkness."
くらやみ:darkness/the dark, ではある:to be (in contrast to something that is not the case)
私は "くらやみ" ではありませんよ
By the way, Araragi-senpai.
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
ところで阿良々木先輩
Araragi-senpai, you've fallen to
hell, and you've gone on a date,
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 地獄[じごく]:hell, 落ちる[おちる]:to fall down|to be omitted|to decrease||, デート:date/go on a date
阿良々木先輩には 地獄に落ち
デートもして
so you may have nothing you look
back on with regret anymore.
思い残す[おもいのこす]:to regret, しれる:to become known/to come to light|to be known
もう思い残すことはないかもしれませんけれど
But I currently have one thing that I
look back on with regret in this town.
現在[げんざい]:now/current/present, 町[まち, ちょう]:town|street|109.09 m||, 思い残す[おもいのこす]:to regret, ことがある:(something) has occurred/to have done (something)|(something) happens on occasions
私には現在 ひとつ
この町で思い残していることがありましてね
Something you look back on with regret?
思い残す[おもいのこす]:to regret
思い残していること?
Something you wouldn't
mind dying to achieve...
やり遂げる[やりとげる]:to accomplish/to finish/to carry through
それをやり遂げるためなら死んでもいいし
Once you achieved this, you wouldn't mind if you died.
Do you have such a goal, Araragi-senpai?
やり遂げる[やりとげる]:to accomplish/to finish/to carry through, 目標[めじるし]:mark/sign/landmark, 目標[もくひょう]:mark/objective/target, 先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
それをやり遂げたら死んでもいいという目標が
阿良々木先輩にはありますか?
I have one. I have just one more.
私にはあるのです
あとひとつだけ あるのです
That's why I have to do it even if I
have to put everything else aside.
だから何をおいても
それをしなければならないのですけれど
That is why if Izuko Gaen, the leader of the
specialists, were to place a trap, it would be there.
専門家[せんもんか]:specialist/expert/professional, 元締め[もとじめ]:manager/boss/controller, 湖[みずうみ]:lake, 湖[こ]:lake (in place names), 罠[わな]:snare/trap (for catching wild game, etc.)|trap (i.e. ruse, subterfuge, etc.), 張る[はる]:to stick|to stretch|to form (e.g. ice on a pond)||, 張る[ばる]:to be prominently .../to be persistently ...
だからこそ 専門家の元締め
臥煙伊豆湖が罠を張るとすれば そこなのでしょう
Yes, I know.
ええ わかっています
I know, but I still have
to fall for that trap...
罠[わな]:snare/trap (for catching wild game, etc.)|trap (i.e. ruse, subterfuge, etc.), 引っかかる[ひっかかる]:to be caught in|to stop by|to get mixed up in (trouble)||
わかっていても
その罠には引っかかるしかない
I have to resign myself to
suffer that counterattack.
反撃[はんげき]:counterattack/counteroffensive/counterblow, 甘んずる[あまんずる]:to content oneself with/to be resigned to (one's fate)/to be contented (satisfied) with (one's lot), 受ける[うける, ウケる]:to receive|to catch (e.g. a ball)|to be struck by (wind, waves, sunlight, etc.)||
その反撃を
私は甘んじて受けるしかない
In other words, starting right now, I am going to
fight the big sister that knows everything,
正面[しょうめん]:front/frontage/facade, 正面[まとも]:the front|honesty|decency, 切る[きる]:to cut|to sever (connections, ties)|to turn off (e.g. the light)||, 誤魔化し[ごまかし]:hanky-panky/juggling/cheating, 戦う[たたかう]:to make war (on)|to compete (against)|to struggle (against adversities, etc.), ことになる:it has been decided (so) that/it has been arranged (so) that|it is the result (of)
つまり 私はこれから 正面切って誤魔化しなく
何でも知ってるおねーさんと戦うことになるのですけれど
with a frontal assault,
with no fudging around...
Araragi-senpai, in this fight,
can you be on my side?
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 味方[みかた]:friend/ally/supporter
阿良々木先輩 そのときは
私の味方をしてくれませんか?
Please, help me.
助ける[たすける]:to save|to help|to aid|, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
私を助けてください